בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is נ"ט. Nun-tet. We pick
up at the bottom of נ"ח עמוד ב' Nun-chet amud bet
and we're dealing with the question about the location of the מזבח,
Mizbeach, and part of it was figuring out is it all in
the north, all in the south, half and half? Half and half
makes nice sense. And part of it was dealing
with this statement that the fire that they used for the burning
of the קטורת, Ketoret, when they tried to bring it into the
קודש Kodesh for the daily twice burning of the קטורת Ketoret or
when they burned on שבת Shabbos the לבונה Levonah and they brought
it out to the altar, that that fire was in the southwest
corner four אמות amot removed from the edge. What does that tell
you about where it's located? Because the point is to get it
opposite the door. So does that mean that it was all in
the north and at maximum it could be removed four אמות amot
from the ledge? Or does that mean it was all in the
south and it had to at minimum be removed four אמות amot
from the edge? And then the question is also where you count
the edge from? Okay. So we didn't conclude. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, but anyway the claim was that רבי יוסי
Reb Yosi is of the opinion that it's all in the north,
which corresponds to his position in the משנה Mishnah that you can
שחט shacht it anywhere on the top of the altar. But as
the גמרא Gemara said, those are really not linked positions. The altar
could be in one place or another and there could still be,
you could be open to different opinions about where you can שחט
shacht something at the top of the altar. So now the גמרא
Gemara says like this, two lines from the bottom on נ"ח עמוד
ב'. Nun-chet amud bet. ורב שרביא אמר, VeRav Shravya amar, רב שרביא
Rav Shravya says, הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא. Ha mani Reb
Yosi HaGlili hi. This is, the idea that it's all in the
north is רבי יוסי הגלילי, Reb Yosi HaGlili, based on a different
evidence, not the evidence about where the fire was. Okay, דתניא detanya
we saw in the ברייתא, braita, רבי יוסי הגלילי אומר, Reb Yosi
HaGlili omer, מתוך שנאמר, Mi-toch shene'emar, where did you put the כיור,
kiyor, the laver? One verse says ונתת את הכיור בין אהל מועד
ובין המזבח, Venatata et hakiyor bein ohel moed uvein hamizbeach, it's between
the אהל מועד ohel moed and the מזבח, mizbeach, and
that's one פסוק. pasuk. And then another פסוק pasuk says ואת מזבח
העולה פתח אהל מועד, Ve-et mizbeach ha'olah petach ohel moed, ולא כיור
velo kiyor בפתח אהל מועד. befetach ohel moed.
So it has to be between the מזבח mizbeach and the אהל
מועד, ohel moed, but it can't get between the מזבח mizbeach and
the opening, the door, because it says only thing facing the door
is the מזבח. mizbeach. Right, which makes a lot of nice sense,
the whole point we spoke about, about the whole zone that the
slaughtering is פתח אהל מועד, petach ohel moed, that somehow that sense
of the door represents the access, right? So you don't want anything
interfering with where you're bringing the קרבנות korbanot and the door that's
getting you the access to the Holy of Holies, obviously anthropomorphically, metaphorically,
you're trying to access the שכינה Shechinah that is inside. I don't
think one precludes the other. It does not preclude the other, correct,
because there's the אהל מועד ohel moed and there's the פתח אהל
מועד. petach ohel moed. So here's your אולם, ulam, I mean there's
your היכל, heichal, and here's your אולם, ulam, okay, oops,
this is 10 and this is 20, okay, right? You have it
drawn down below. I know, I know, but I wanted a bigger
picture. It is true, I don't know why I had to draw
it again, but anyway. Okay, and okay, got a nice blue marker
thanks to חנה. Chanah. Now, okay, where are you going to put
it? Right, the מזבח, mizbeach, I mean we'll figure out where the
מזבח mizbeach is, but let's assume the מזבח mizbeach is like centered
or whatever, as long as you put it, right? The מזבח mizbeach
is 32. So if you figure that the מזבח mizbeach is centered,
right, I mean, okay, it's a square, whatever, as long as, bit
too much of a perfectionist anyway. All right, so you can put
it up here, but we're going to see you don't want it
in the north because you want the north clear because a lot
of things are done in the north and we're going to learn
from a פסוק pasuk that you don't want anything else in the
north, like not just you don't want it, you're not allowed to.
But fine, you can put it here, right? If this is 20
and this is 32, there's 11 on, there's what is it, six
on each side. Okay, and so if you don't want in front
of the door of the אולם ulam and you don't want in
front of the door of the היכל, heichal, you have even more
space, you have 11 on each side, right, 11. So you just
put it in the space that's between the מזבח mizbeach and the
אהל מועד, ohel moed, right, but that is not in front of
the door. Okay, so that's easy. You just put it here somewhere,
okay, and it's not in front of the door and you should
be fine. So let's see what the issue is going to be
though. Okay, I would say just based on the פסוק, pasuk, מזבח
העולה פתח mizbeach ha'olah petach or whatever, I mean, you know, I'm
thinking of like a big thing, I don't view this כיור kiyor
as being so huge that it would be considered even if you
put it פתח. petach. Oh, you're just saying that no, but you
know, the גמרא Gemara understands that it's like that's absolute. Okay, so
let's take a look. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, and by the way, remember the statement before, which is important
to keep in mind just for those that were about to ask,
that it said that the edges of the מזבח mizbeach are exactly
in line, if you include the walls, the edges of, I'm sorry,
the edges of our מזבח mizbeach are exactly in line with the
היכל, heichal, but not just the cavity of the היכל, heichal, but
the entire היכל. heichal. So anywhere you put it, it's going to
be between the מזבח mizbeach if it's centered, between the מזבח mizbeach
and the אהל מועד ohel moed is going to be between the
מזבח mizbeach and the אהל מועד ohel moed because these line up.
Just don't put it in the way of the door and you
should be fine. Okay, so let's take a look. The גמרא Gemara
says like this
now. מזבח פתח אהל מועד ולא כיור פתח אהל מועד. Mizbeach petach
ohel moed velo kiyor petach ohel moed. היכן היה נותנו? Heichan haya
nosno? בין האולם ולמזבח. Bein haulam velamizbeach. משוך קימעא כלפי הדרום. mashuch
kima klafey hadarom. Between the אולם ulam and
the מזבח, mizbeach, so here is the אולם, ulam, but a little
bit to the south. Now, משוך, mashuch, a little bit drawn to
the south from where? So the גמרא Gemara assumes what it means
is from the edge of the מזבח. mizbeach. Then actually you would
put it here, okay, which is certainly not ideal. I mean, you
could say that is בין האולם ולמזבח, bein ha-ulam velamizbeach, you know,
it is between, you know, what's the פסוק? pasuk? בין אהל מועד
ובין המזבח bein ohel moed uvein hamizbeach because it's in the space
between the אהל מועד ובין המזבח, ohel moed uvein hamizbeach, but it
is not ideal ideal, you would want it directly, you know, between
the two, right? So why are we having to move it south
from the edge? So it's only in that sort of, you know,
that vertical space between them, but not literally between them. Why not
put it over here? And we're going to and we're going to
sort of and the only answer we're going to come up with
is because all of this is in the north and we're going
to assume you can't put anything else in the north. And only
because all of this is in the north and you can't put
anything else in the north, this has to be removed from the
southern edge, even more even more south than the southern edge of
the מזבח. mizbeach. Because otherwise there's plenty of space to put it
there without getting in the way of the door. So let's take
a look at that. Okay, now. Why would it get in the
way? Is there is there a concern that it would get in
the way when the כהן kohen has to go to that fire
that's on the... No, no, no, this is on the floor. Oh,
no, he can avoid it. It's not it's not filling up the
space. But you are right. I mean if anywhere it is you
got a you know you gotta maneuver around it because it's right
in the way of the route. You are correct with that. All
right. Well I like it there, you know, by where the ramp
is, it's close, he's gonna have to go up the ramp anyway
so get as close to the bottom of the ramp as you
can. Right. Okay, so it says like this, it says, oh, that's
a good point. Okay, anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like this.
I don't know, I like symmetry. Anyway says the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, now, מאי קסבר? mai kasavar?
What's the opinion that it has to be below the southernmost edge
of the מזבח? mizbeach? אי קסבר כולי מזבח בדרום קאי, ee kasavar
kulei mizbeach bedarom kaei, if the entire מזבח mizbeach is in the
south, נוקמיה מכותל היכל ולהדרום בין אולם ולמזבח. nokmih mikotel heichal ulahadarom
bein ulam ulamizbeach.
So okay, if the whole thing is in the south, put it
between the wall of the היכל heichal and to the southern half,
doesn't I mean everything is in the southern half, doesn't really matter,
between it, between the אולם ulam and the מזבח. mizbeach. Okay, meaning
again, if this thing is half and half then there's still space
as I said there's 6 even between the edge of the door
of the אולם ulam there's 6 אמה ammah on each side and
certainly there's more space from the opening of the אהל מועד. ohel
moed. So if it's half and half and you've got space in
the south to put it without interfering with the door, if the
whole thing is in the south of course you have space to
put it without interfering with the door. Okay, ואי נמי קסבר ve-ee
nami kasavar and even if you hold קדושת היכל ואולם חדא היא
kedushat heichal ve-ulam chada hi that we look at the אולם ulam
and the היכל heichal as one unit so it can't be the
door of the אולם ulam has the same status as the door
of the היכל heichal so it can't be in between the door
of the אולם ulam and the מזבח. mizbeach. נוקמיה מכותל אולם ולהדרום
בין אולם ולמזבח. nokmih mikotel ulam ulahadarom bein ulam ulamizbeach. You still
have space in the south to put it, right, to put it
between the מזבח mizbeach and the walls of the אולם ulam and
not get in the way of the door of the אולם. ulam.
ואי נמי קסבר ve-ee nami kasavar
and now this is even more, so I didn't even bother working
that through with you because if it's all in the south it's
obvious you have that space. But ואי נמי קסבר חציו בצפון וחציו
בדרום ve-ee nami kasavar chetzyo batzafon vechetzyo bedarom even if it's half
and half, נוקמיה מכותל היכל ולהדרום בין אולם ומזבח. nokmih mikotel heichal
ulahadarom bein ulam umizbeach.
So fine, put it from the wall, meaning the wall after you're
done with the door, okay, so this is the wall, put it
in front of the wall of the היכל heichal and the מזבח
mizbeach and it's between the אולם ulam and the מזבח mizbeach and
it's and it's at least directly in that space between and it's
away from the opening, right? Because if this is 10 then you've
got on each side of here if it's 32 you've got 11,
you've got plenty of space. ואי נמי קסבר קדושת אולם והיכל חדא
היא ve-ee nami kasavar kedushat ulam ve-heichal chada hi
and even if the אולם ulam and the היכל heichal is one
unit so it can't be in the way of the door of
the אולם ulam either, נוקמיה מכותל אולם ולהדרום בין אולם ולמזבח. nokmih
mikotel ulam ulahadarom bein ulam ulamizbeach.
So okay, but you still have a wall of the אולם ulam
in the south, right? This is 20, the opening of the אולם
ulam and you have 6 on each side that's opposite the מזבח.
mizbeach. So you still have space to put it, okay? So there's
plenty of space to put it if this stuff is centered or
all in the south. The only where it's not put it is
if it's all in the north and we assume it can't be
in the north, okay? So אלא ella must be לאו משום דקסבר
כולי מזבח בצפון. lav mishum dekasavar kulei mizbeach batzafon. It's all in
the north. So the גמרא Gemara says okay, it's all in the
north. Put it in the north, right? I started by telling you
that you're not allowed to put it in the north. But if
you don't know that, it's like okay, the whole מזבח mizbeach is
in the north, put it in the north of the you know
of the עזרה azarah when it's not directly in front of the
door. So the גמרא Gemara says כי נמי מוקמינן לה מכותל היכל
ולצפון הוי בין אולם ומזבח. ki nami mokminan lah mikotel heichal uletzafon
havei bein ulam umizbeach. Okay, so if so what?
So put it between the wall of the היכל heichal and to
the north and it'll be between the אולם ulam and the מזבח.
mizbeach. Why do you have to draw it down to the south?
ונוקמיה מכותל
אולם ולצפון בין אולם ומזבח. venokmih mikotel ulam uletzafon bein ulam umizbeach.
Anyway אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says צפונה. tzafona. It says
על ירך המזבח צפונה, al yerech hamizbeach tzafona, you slaughter something in
the north, שצפון פנוי מכלום. shetzafon panui miklum.
Somehow we're learning from the word צפונה, tzafona, nothing else can be
in the north. The only thing can be the מזבח, mizbeach, you
can't put extraneous things in the north. Okay, which is by the
way interesting, because if the only place you can שחט shacht is
directly to the north of the מזבח mizbeach itself, okay, then the
space between the אולם ulam and the מזבח, mizbeach, how do we
know that also has to be clear? Right? I mean if you're
supposed to שחט shacht only here, right? I think if I remember
correctly there's a question if you can שחט shacht more inner. But
anyway, but it's interesting that we're assuming that this gap between also
has to be clear as well. All right? By the way, little
bit little parenthesis, תוספות, tosfot, look at תוספות. tosfot. תוספות tosfot says
פנוי מכלום. panui miklum. תוספות tosfot says אף על פי שמזבח שעשה
משה af al pi shemizbeach she’asah moshe כלי היה. kli hayah. But
okay. So, but in the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, this was like
a structure, the מזבח. mizbeach. It was connected to the ground, it
was huge. But in the time of משה moshe it was a
movable vessel, so that wasn't clear of everything. The מזבח mizbeach itself
was in the north. כדאמר דנין כלי מכלי ואין דנין כלי מבנין.
ked’amar danin kli mikli ve’ein danin kli mibinyan. משאר כלים קאמר. mish’ar
keilim ka’amar. No, it means north of everything else, other than the
מזבח. mizbeach. Even if the מזבח mizbeach itself was a כלי, kli,
was movable in the time of משה. moshe. דצפון המזבח קאמר. detzafon
hamizbeach ka’amar. ואף על פי שהיה צפון הננסים וכלונסאות ושולחנות, ve’af al
pi shehayah tzafon hananasim vechlonasot veshulchanot, תוספות's tosfot got a problem. We
learned elsewhere that they had a whole all this slaughter apparatus there.
They had tables and hooks and posts. It wasn't clear of everything.
מסתמא האי דאמר תורה פנוי מכלום, mistama hai de’amar torah panui miklum,
when we say it has to be empty of everything, משום שחיטה
הוא. mishum shechitah hu. It has to be
that's because you want to give space to do the שחיטה. shechitah.
And especially by the עולה. olah. By the עולה olah this is
the only space you have, so don't clutter this up with anything
else. We need the space for the עולה, olah, I mean not
עולה, olah, קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. Okay, since it's all all קדשי
קדשים kodshei kodashim have to be in this space, don't put other
things here. But because we're שחט-ing shacht things here, obviously you can
put stuff here that's related to the שחיטה. shechitah. כי הני צורכי
שחיטה נינהו. ki hanei tzoreich shechitah ninhu. So that's interesting. Interesting understanding
that the תורה torah needed to clear it out of other stuff
because you needed to שחט shacht קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, but obviously
apparatus for שחיטה shechitah you can have. So if it's all in
the north and you're not allowed to put anything in the north
that's not directly related to שחיטה shechitah כשיטת תוספות, keshitat tosfot, the
only thing where place you can put this is by drawing it
to the south. Okay, so then it would be, right? So if
this is now, right,
all in the north like that, then you're going to the there's
no way you can put this here and you're going to have
to draw it. And actually you're going to have to draw it
at least at least five אמות. amos. Because you gotta get it
at least away from the door of the of the אולם. ulam.
And the door of the אולם ulam is five אמות amos off
to each side. And it's only בין אולם ולמזבח bein ulam u’lemizbeach
in the sense that it's in that vertical strip, but it's not
directly between the אולם ulam and the מזבח. mizbeach. What's the matter
there, David? Doesn't correspond to your picture? Well, there are a lot
of pictures. This this one have the כיור kiyor actually directly across
but to the south of the altar being in the north. Right,
it is. But oh no, no, no. No, oh you know what?
You're right actually. Because that's actually an excellent point. So for once
I מודה modeh to the picture there. Which is that it actually
can be in front of the door. I wasn't thinking about that.
Because the הלכה halachah isn't that the כיור kiyor cannot be in
front of the door. The הלכה halachah is that the כיור kiyor
can't get between the door and the מזבח. mizbeach. So actually that's
an excellent point. In this configuration that the entire מזבח mizbeach is
in the north, the כיור kiyor could be just like a like
just like a טפח tefach below and it could be in front
of the door. I mean it's still probably not a good place
to put it. You'd run into it. You'd probably still want to
move it. But technically it could be because the הלכה halachah isn't
that it can't be in front of the door. The הלכה halachah
is it can't interrupt the door and the מזבח. mizbeach. Good point.
Good good correction. Okay, so now the גמרא gemara says like this.
Okay,
so that proves that he holds that it's all in the north.
מאן תנא דפליג עליה דרבי יוסי הגלילי? man tanna depalig alei derabbi
yose haglili?
Now who argues on רבי יוסי הגלילי? rabbi yose haglili? Meaning we've
just dealt with the reasonable possibility that it's half and half. We've
dealt with the position of רבי יוסי rabbi yose or רבי יוסי
הגלילי rabbi yose haglili or somebody that we want to say has
it all in the north. What we're missing is the third possibility.
I mean obviously there's an infinite number of possibilities, but we're missing
the like the simple third possibility which is it's all in the
south. Okay, and now we're going to introduce that one. Right? Could
have a טפח tefach in the north, two טפחים tefachim in the
north, there's an infinite number of possibilities. But anyway. Okay, so who's
the תנא tanna that argues on רבי יוסי הגלילי? rabbi yose haglili?
רבי אלעזר בן יעקב rabbi eliezer ben yaakov is. רבי אלעזר בן
יעקב. rabbi eliezer ben yaakov. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא,
braisa, רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר rabbi eliezer ben yaakov omer צפונה
tzafona שהיא צפון פנוי מכלום. shehi tzafon panui miklum. Not it should
be free from everything... before the דרשה drashah was מן כלים, min
keilim, free from vessels. Here the דרש drash is מכלום. miklum. It
has to be free from everything. אפילו מן המזבח. afilu min hamizbeach.
You can't have even any part of the altar in the north.
Okay, so therefore the entire altar was in the south, which from
the functional point of giving more space for the שחיטה shechitah of
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim makes a lot of sense. Okay,
so.
ואפילו מזה. ve’afilu mizeh. אמר רב מזבח שנפגם. amar rav mizbeach shenifgam.
but I do like the point that Michael made which is if
the whole מזבח mizbei’ach is in the north, it makes the work
easier for the כהנים kohanim because it’s less distance travel when they
come down off the ramp, at least a little less distance, whatever.
Okay, now we are done with the location of the מזבח. mizbei’ach.
That was a lot of fun I thought so. Anyway, now we
get onto a related point, but not a location point. אמר רב
Amar Rav says
Rav, מזבח שנפגם כל הקדשים שנשחטו שם פסולים. mizbei’ach shenifgam kol ha’kodashim
she’nishchatu sham psulim. If the altar was chipped, you know, was a
piece of it was, I want to say injured, but that's not
the right word, damaged I guess, but it's more the sense of
נפגם nifgam means like a piece came off, chipped I guess. If
the altar was chipped, okay, it's not whole, any sacrifices that are
slaughtered and the interesting phrase here is שנשחטו שם, she’nishchatu sham, no
actually שנשחטו שם she’nishchatu sham from the moment it was chipped on,
but not like that whole day and not like you go by
חזקה, chazakah, that's an interesting חולין Chullin question. You found it chipped
in the middle of the day, do you have to worry retroactively?
No, presumably not. Where's the... No, three opinions. Okay, now, if the
altar was chipped, all קדשים kodshim that were שחט shechted from the
moment that it was chipped, in that context, פסולים psulim are invalid.
מקרא הוא בידינו ושכחנוהו. Mikra hu bi’yadeinu ve’shachachnuhu. I love this. Actually,
we had a פסוק pasuk that proved this. I remember the הלכה
halacha but I don't remember the פסוק pasuk it was based on.
Okay, there's something interestingly like symbolic about that, about like trying to
reconstruct, you know, the lost מקדש. Mikdash. I mean, I'm not saying
you only have this by the world of קדשים, kodshim, but the
idea like what we've retained is the הלכה. halacha. We haven't actually
like retained the actual experience of it. You know? Why can't we
just say it's not considered a מזבח mizbei’ach if it's chipped? Okay,
but you need a פסוק pasuk to show you that. Who says
that the מזבח mizbei’ach has to be... I mean, you need a
פסוק. pasuk. Okay, and you need a פסוק pasuk also to say
that it invalidates the שחיטה. shechitah. Let's say I שחט shechted it
and then I went ahead and before I threw the blood, I
fixed it. How do you know that the שחיטה shechitah is invalid?
So it's two points. You're right. A, you could just say by
סברא sevara it's not considered a כשר מזבח, kosher mizbei’ach, but you'd
have to say why not. But B, you have to invalidate the
שחיטה. shechitah. Okay, what's that famous story they tell? Is it a
רב נחמן Rav Nachman story or whatever about how, you know, it
used to be like the Rebbe would go to the forest and
he would sing the special ניגון niggun and they do the special
song and then says then the next generation like we lost the,
you know,
the somehow like the special kabbalistic sort of words he would say,
but we retained the song and then and the dance and then
next... and now all we have left is the story. You know?
And now what we have left is the story of the story.
Anyway, so okay, so anyway, so that's what we have. We had
this, we had this, we had a פסוק, pasuk, but now we
just know the הלכה. halacha. We don't know the פסוק. pasuk. כי
סליק רב כהנא Ki salik Rav Kahana when רב כהנא Rav Kahana
went to ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. There's a nice thing here like
going back to where the בית המקדש Beis Ha’Mikdash was, you know,
you're going back to the source. He went to ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, אשכחיה לרב שמעון ברבי. ashkachei le’Rav Shimon be’Rabbi. He found רב
שמעון Rav Shimon the son of רבי, Rabbi, רבי יהודה הנשיא, Rabbi
Yehuda Ha’Nasi, דקאמר משמיה דרבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. de’ka’amar mishmei de’Rabbi Yishmael
be’Rabbi Yosi. Said in the name of רבי ישמעאל ברבי יוסי. Rabbi
Yishmael be’Rabbi Yosi. Okay, which, what did he say? מניין למזבח שנפגם
שכל הקדשים שנשחטו שם פסולים? Minayin le’mizbei’ach shenifgam she’kol ha’kodashim she’nishchatu sham
psulim? How do you know that if it was damaged all the
sacrifices that were slaughtered are invalid, that even the שחיטה shechitah is
invalid? שנאמר וזבחת עליו את עלותיך ואת שלמיך, shene’emar ve’zavachta alav et
olotecha ve’et shelammecha, on it. וכי עליו הוא זובח? Ve’chi alav hu
zove’ach? Do you literally slaughter on it? And this is why it's
linked to our משנה mishnah because the משנה mishnah actually says yes,
you can שחט shecht at the top of the altar. And they
base it on this פסוק. pasuk. It's a very literal read of
this פסוק, pasuk, slaughter on it. But what the גמרא Gemara is
actually here doing is it's going back to more פשט peshat of
the read. The פשט peshat is not, it's funny, the פשט peshat
is not the literal meaning of it. I mean, you know, the
literal meaning of עליו. alav. It's not a hyper-literalistic... anyway, you know,
because it doesn't mean literally on it, it means sort of against
it, in reference to it. Okay, so the שחיטה shechitah takes place
in reference to, in correspondence to the altar. So connected to the
altar. And therefore the altar has to be a whole. וכי עליו
אתה זובח? Ve’chi alav attah zove’ach? You don't literally slaughter on it,
even though you are allowed. אלא כשהוא שלם ולא כשהוא חסר, Ella
keshu shalem ve’lo keshu chaser, slaughter in reference to the altar, so
the slaughtering is in the context of the altar. And yes, it
is like Michael was saying, it assumes that if the altar isn't
whole, it's not an altar. It's not full. It doesn't have to
be this size, but whatever size it has to be it can't
be chipped, it can't be damaged. Okay. And but this פסוק pasuk
teaches you the שחיטה shechitah takes place in reference to the altar.
But this damage is like, you know, a big hole? It's not
like a damage in the little, you know, plaster over it? Yeah,
that's always a question of how much of a damage. It's like
when you return your car, you got a little scratch. Oh, it
doesn't really... anyway, or it depends, they have to discuss it with
them. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ולא כשהוא חסר. ve’lo keshu
chaser. אמר היינו קרא דאישתלי ליה לרב. Amar hainu kra de’ishtali leh
le’Rav. This is the פסוק pasuk that Rav had forgotten. Thank you!
ורבי יוחנן אמר אחד זה ואחד זה פסולים. Ve’Rabbi Yochanan amar echad
zeh ve’echad zeh psulim. Now Rabbi Yochanan says that not only is
it invalid if you שחט shechted it, it's even invalid... hold on,
let me just check רש"י. Rashi. One minute. Hold on, hold on.
What's the אחד זה? echad zeh? אחד זה... echad zeh... Meaning whether
it was שחט *shecht*ed when it was, when it was, had been
chipped, or whether even it wasn't שחט *shecht*ed when it had been
chipped, okay, even if it had been שחט *shecht*ed after it had
been fixed. If it went through a time when it had been
chipped, even if the animal was alive, it's invalid. And this is
the principle, this is the principle, yes, you were מקדיש *makdish* your
animal, and then the מזבח mizbeach. *mizbe'ach* got chipped, and they have
to send out a recall notice by an email blast, I don't
know how they would tell everybody, or maybe when you would come
to the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash. *beis hamikdash* they would ask you,
oh by the way, when were you מקדיש *makdish* your עולה *olah*?
Oh well, if it's anytime between, if you had מקדיש *makdish*ed it
anytime prior to, you know, 12:07 Monday afternoon, you know, whatever, then
it's invalid because it had been chipped then, because it's a principle
of דיחוי *dichuy*. That it was, it went through a time when
it couldn't be slaughtered. That's Rav Yochanan's principle, that there's דיחוי *dichuy*
by בעלי חיים *ba'alei chayim*. But if I'm away from פסח המועד
*pesach hamoyid* it can't be slaughtered either, so you think there's a
מזבח mizbeach. *mizbe'ach* but it can't be slaughtered. It's an interesting question,
like would it have to be brought to the מקדש *mikdash* to
be in the context. Normally when we say בעלי חיים נדחין *ba'alei
chayim nidchin* you don't have to be, you know, physically right there.
Like the classic example the גמרא gemara *gemara* about בעלי חיים נדחין
*ba'alei chayim nidchin* is a guy becomes a מום mum. *mum* and
then he does תשובה *teshuva*. And we say the הלכה *halacha* is,
if you say בעלי חיים *ba'alei chayim* is נדחה *nidcheh*, since the
קרבן *korban* couldn't be brought when he was a מום mum, *mum*,
means even if you can't be brought anyway, he's a thousand miles
away. But no, if you were in the בית המקדש *beis hamikdash*
you couldn't bring it right now, so that's a דיחוי *dichuy*. So
here, anytime it got chipped, anybody who's got a קרבן *korban* right
now that is sanctified, that קרבן *korban* is invalid, and I guess
we have to have a sign up and inform people until it
gets fixed. Okay, it's like you know you have the עירוב *eruv*
notice. Right, exactly. Rav Yochanan סבר *savar*, okay, so the גמרא gemara
*gemara* says Rav Yochanan אמר *amar*, אחד זה ואחד זה פסולין *echad
zeh v'echad zeh psulin*, פסול pasul. *posul* even if it wasn't slaughtered,
even if it was just sanctified at that time. במאי פלגי *b'mai
palgi*, what's the debate about? Rav סבר *savar*, בעלי חיים אינם נדחין
*ba'alei chayim einam nidchin*. If it's on a live animal it doesn't
get pushed away. When something is alive it's more dynamic, it's not
like its identity is static, and therefore, even though there's a period
it can't be brought, you know, as long as it gets fixed
before it gets slaughtered it's okay. Rav Yochanan סבר *savar*, בעלי חיים
נדחין *ba'alei chayim nidchin*. No, even if it's alive and it's sanctified,
obviously only after it's sanctified, you know, then if it goes through
a period it can't be brought, that gets stigmatized and pushed away.
Okay, מיתיבי *meisvei*, I'll ask you. כל הקדשים שהיו עד שלא נבנה
המזבח ואחר כך נבנה המזבח פסולין *kol hakodashim shehayu ad shelo nivneh
hamizbe'ach v'achar kach nivneh hamizbe'ach psulin*. So we assume this means that
in the time when they were returning in the בית שני *bayis
sheini*. All things that had been sanctified, people were getting maybe very
excited, they were building the בית המקדש *beis hamikdash*, so all things
that were sanctified before the altar was built and then the altar
was built, פסולין *psulin*. They are invalid. So that seems to be
a support of Rav Yochanan. The only problem is it's a little
too much of a support because this is something that was never
fit for being brought as a קרבן *korban*. Okay, there's two different
major questions about דיחוי *dichuy*. One is בעלי חיים *ba'alei chayim*, can
something be pushed away even when it's alive? And the other is
the difference between נראה ונדחה *nir'ah v'nidcheh* and דיחוי מעיקרא *dichuy mei'ikara*.
נראה ונדחה *nir'ah v'nidcheh* means you're in the פרשה *parsha* and therefore,
you know, there was a period you were fit and then you
were invalidated. Right, if you got fired from a job, good luck
trying to get rehired. If you didn't get hired in the first
place, the first time you might come back a year later trying
to get hired again, resubmit your application. Okay, so דיחוי מעיקרא *dichuy
mei'ikara* is less of a stigma than נראה ונדחה *nir'ah v'nidcheh*. נראה
ונדחה *nir'ah v'nidcheh* is you were in the פרשה *parsha* and pushed
away. דיחוי מעיקרא *dichuy mei'ikara* was you were never in, that makes
it easier to try again. All right, so the גמרא gemara *gemara*
says this statement that the animals that they had that they sanctified
when they were building the מקדש *mikdash* and building the מזבח mizbeach
*mizbe'ach* are פסול *posul* is even more severe than Rav Yochanan. It's
not only דיחוי *dichuy* of בעלי חיים *ba'alei chayim*, it's even דיחוי
מעיקרא *dichuy mei'ikara* because it was never fit. And why is that
true? It's not so clear דיחוי מעיקרא *dichuy mei'ikara* is a problem.
So the גמרא gemara *gemara* says נבנה *nivneh*, דיחוי מעיקרא *dichuy mei'ikara*
is it? That's דיחוי מעיקרא *dichuy mei'ikara* if they were in the
process of being built. אלא עד שלא נהרס המזבח *ella ad shelo
neras hamizbe'ach*. Okay, no no, here's what it means. It means something
you had sanctified before the first בית המקדש *beis hamikdash* was destroyed,
and you and your animal lived a long time, and you came
back seventy years later, okay, I don't know if animals live seventy
years, you came back seventy years later, and now the מזבח mizbeach.
*mizbe'ach* is being rebuilt, this animal is פסול *posul* because it went
through those seventy years without a מזבח mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*. So that's a
דיחוי *dichuy* of בעלי חיים *ba'alei chayim* but it's a נראה ונדחה
*nir'ah v'nidcheh*. So the גמרא Gemara *gemara* says נהרס *neras*, destroyed, האיזקן
להו *ha'izkan lehu*, the animal is too old, can't be used, it's
like considered a מום *mum* if it's that old, I don't even
know if it could live seventy years. אלא *ella* fine, עד שלא
נפגם המזבח ואחר כך נפגם המזבח פסולין *ad shelo nifgam hamizbe'ach v'achar
kach nifgam hamizbe'ach psulin*. Okay, so the only way to read this
ברייתא braita *braita* is if you had an animal before the altar
got chipped, and then the altar got chipped. then it's invalid. So
that's a נראה ונדחה, but it's a דיחוי בבעלי חיים. dichuy be-ba'alei
chayim. So with all those corrections, it supports רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
So the גמרא Gemara says once you're making corrections, it can't support
anything. So the גמרא Gemara says, ולו תרצה כמתרצא, ve-lo tirtza kematartza,
look, you've already edited that ברייתא braita, up, so אימא שנישחט, eima
shenishchat, once you're fixing it to say that the animal was sanctified
and then it got chipped and then it got fixed, I'll read
it to say the animal was sanctified and then it got chipped
and then it got slaughtered and then it got fixed. So when
you're, you know, if you're so editing the ברייתא, braita, then it
doesn't prove anything. Rashi refers to the seventy-year gap, but he talks
about it הלכתית, halachically, he says, עד דלא נבנה בית שני פשיטא
דפסולין דגבי מומין קתני להו בבכור והקדש והמעשר. ad dela nivnei bayit
sheni peshita de-pesulin de-gabi mumin katani lehu be-bechor ve-ha-kodesh ve-ha-ma'aser. Right, ואפילו
הכי חזו למזבח. ve-afilu hachi chazu lamizbeach. I know, I know I
said that, right, that it's considered a מום. If very old is
a מום, I just don't know if seventy years, somebody could do
on their Google and see if a cow lives seventy years, I'm
betting the answer is no, but who knows, I don't know, I'm
not a farmer. Okay, so fine. Okay, והאמר רב גידל אמר רב
מזבח שנעקר מקטירין קטורת במקומו, ve-ha-amar Rav Gidal amar Rav mizbeach shene'ekar
maktirin ktoret bimkomo, one minute. How can you say that if it's
damaged you can't go ahead and do the sacrifices? We say if
the golden altar, the inner altar, the incense altar is removed, you
can use the floor underneath, you can even offer directly on the
ground. You don't even need a מזבח. mizbeach, If that's a fascinating
idea that you could have קדושת מזבח kedushat mizbeach to that space
without it being the actual physical מזבח. mizbeach. Doesn't he say מזבח
שנעקר מקטירין קטורת במקומו? mizbeach shene'ekar maktirin ktoret bimkomo? So the גמרא
Gemara says, כי דאמר רבא, ki de-amar Rava, no, like רבא Rava
says in a different context which we'll get to in a minute,
מודה היה רבי יהודה בדמים. modeh haya Rabbi Yehuda be-damim. רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda would agree that blood is different than the incense. We
might have allowed a certain thing for incense, but we won't allow
it for blood. So we'll see that context in a minute, but
הכא נמי hacha nami here too, מודה רב בדמים. modeh Rav be-damim.
When רב Rav says that the שחיטה shechita needs the altar, he's
talking about stuff relating to the blood. Okay, but the blood stuff
as we know is all much weightier, much more central and so
on. So therefore the שחיטה shechita and the blood that's going to
be going on the outer altar, whatever, there the altar has to
be physically present, you need the altar, you can't just use the
space underneath and so on. When it comes to the קטורת, ktoret,
maybe you don't need the altar, by the קטורת ktoret you can
do it right on that space. You know, it's interesting, you also
could have said there's a difference between a damaged מזבח mizbeach and
no מזבח. mizbeach Maybe a damaged is worse than no מזבח, mizbeach
but the גמרא Gemara isn't saying that. Blood and שחיטה shechita needs
the מזבח, mizbeach וקטורת ve-ktoret really you could do without the מזבח.
mizbeach, Fascinating idea. Okay, דמאי רבי יהודה? de-mai Rabbi Yehuda? Now, where
did רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda make this distinction between blood and the
קטורת? ktoret? דתניא, de-tanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, ביום ההוא
קידש המלך את תוך החצר הפנימית כי מזבח הנחושת אשר לפני ה'
קטן מהכיל. bayom hahu kidesh hamelech et toch hechatzer hapnimit ki mizbeach
hanechoshet asher lifnei Hashem katan me-hachil. Okay, so that day they were
bringing all these sacrifices in the dedication of the בית המקדש. שלמה,
Shlomo, it said, sanctified the actual courtyard itself, the עזרה, azara, because
the altar of משה, Moshe, the copper altar, was too small to
contain all the sacrifices that he was doing. He was doing like
twenty-two thousand sacrifices. So the way we're going to read it is,
okay, so he sanctified the courtyard because the altar was too small?
So there's going to be two debates what this means, there's going
to be, no, not two debates, two opinions. There's going to be
a debate. And one opinion is going to mean that what he
actually did was he sanctified the courtyard to use the courtyard as
the מזבח mizbeach itself because there was not a big enough מזבח
mizbeach to actually do, so he was going to actually use the
ground of the courtyard for bringing sacrifices. Okay, the ground of the
עזרה, azara, which seems to be against what we just said. So
we'll take a look. Okay, so קטן מהכיל. katan me-hachil. דברים ככתבן,
devarim ke-chtavan, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says it's like it sounds like. Now, not exactly like it sounds
like, because the way רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads it is, it's
not just that משה's Moshe altar was too small, it's even the
altar that they were going to build in its place was too
small. And because that altar was too small, even the new altar,
okay, the way it's read is like even the substitute altar to
משה's Moshe altar was too small, that's what we're going to read,
they had to sanctify the courtyard itself. Okay, אמר לו רבי יוסי,
amar lo Rabbi Yossi, so רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says to him,
והלא כבר נאמר, ve-halo kvar ne'emar, אלף עולות יעלה שלמה על המזבח
ההוא, elef olot ya'aleh Shlomo al hamizbeach hahu, ואילו בית עולמים הוא
אומר, ve-ilu beit olamim hu omer, ויזבח שלמה זבח שלמים אשר זבח
לה' בקר עשרים ושנים אלף. vayizbach Shlomo zevach shelamim asher zavach la-Hashem
bakar esrim u-shnayim elef. So on the original altar of משה, Moshe,
it says they did a thousand עולות. olot. Okay, on the new,
when at this moment when it's too small and they're sanctifying something,
the court, whatever, the courtyard, we'll
see what they're sanctifying, it says he did twenty-two thousand. So he
did twenty-two times as much this time around than when he did
when he did on the altar of משה. Moshe. Now, וכשאתה מגיע
לחשבון עולות, u-cheshe-ata magia le-cheshbon olot, now if you do the math
regarding the עולות, olot, twenty-two to one ratio, ולמנין אמה, u-le-minyan ama,
and you do the ratio of the size of the altars, זה
גדול מזה. zeh gadol mizeh. So actually the new altar was more
than twenty-two times as big. So there was no need to sanctify
the floor, because actually the new altar could have done twenty-two times
the output, the business, as the old altar. Now what's the math?
How do you get twenty-two times as much? Because we're going to
see there's going to be debate about all of this, not surprisingly,
but we're going to see that the... does anybody remember what it
says in the תורה Torah about how big the מזבח הנחושת mizbe’ach
hanechoshet was? חמש אמות. chamesh amot. Excellent. Five by five by three.
We'll get to the three later. Okay, it's five by five. So
you would think that the space on the top is twenty-five square
אמות. amot. Except we're going to assume that you have your corners
here, which take up an אמה amah on each side, and we're
going to assume that you've got your walk-around. Okay, so if you're
taking up an אמה amah for that and an אמה amah on
each side, and an אמה amah for the walk-around on each side,
we are left with in the middle the entire space to bring
sacrifices is one אמה, amah, one square אמה. amah. Do you see
that? Right, if you've cut two אמות amot here, two אמות amot
here, right, one אמה amah for the corner and one אמה amah
for the walk-around, then you are left with a one אמה amah
by one אמה amah in the middle for actually bringing the sacrifice.
Nothing, right, what is that? It's like smaller than this space right
here, foot and a half. Okay so that one and they did
a thousand עולות olot in one day there. Okay so רש״י Rashi
says God helped. Okay so anyway so the one now this we're
saying is right twenty-eight, right it was thirty-two at the bottom, then
it got to be thirty, then it got to be twenty-eight at
the top. You cut in, cut in again two on each side
for the corners and the walk-around. So now you've got right twenty-four
by twenty-four. Is that right? No, רש״י Rashi has twenty by twenty.
Hold on. It was thirty-two, thirty, twenty-eight. Why does רש״י Rashi have
twenty by twenty? One second. כ״ו כ״ו. kaf-vav kaf-vav. One minute, כ״ו...
kaf-vav... Okay I'm not sure why it's twenty by twenty. It should
be twenty-four by twenty-four but maybe they used the outer space for
something else as well. Anyway minimally it's it could be as much
as twenty-four by twenty-four but even if it's twenty by twenty, okay
over here it's twenty-eight but anyway you have the corners and whatnot,
that's four hundred times as big. All right so a twenty-two to
one ratio no problem we could do that throughput easily. Okay four
barbeques no waiting. All right anyway so the גמרא Gemara says like
this. Okay so therefore he said you didn't need to sanctify the
floor, the new altar was big enough to handle the business. So
what does it mean that שלמה Shlomo sanctified the חצר? chatzar? It
doesn't mean he sanctified the חצר, chatzar, it doesn't mean he sanctified
the ground to use that for sacrificing, it means he sanctified the
new altar, okay? אלא מה קטן מהיכל, ela mah katan mehichal, what
does it mean that it was too small? Okay so he says
כדי אמר ליה לחבריה פלוני ננס הוא פסול לעבודה. kideh amarei l’chavero
ploni nanas hu pasul l’avodah. It doesn't mean it means that now
it's not exactly clear because he's sort of because it's like I'm
not exactly sure why this specifically problem according to this approach but
he says it doesn't mean it was too small it means like
it wasn't up to the job, it wasn't so it's not so
what bothers me is that it was too small but hold on
let me see what exactly bothers him. Yeah and it's not exactly
clear meaning the first opinion who was it? ר׳ יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
reads it on that day let's go to the פסוק pasuk again.
ביום ההוא קידש המלך תוך החצר כי מזבח הנחושת קטן מהיכל. bayom
hahu kidesh hamelech toch hachatzar ki mizbe’ach hanechoshet katan mehichal. So he
reads it okay the question is like which of these terms are
you going to redefine? ביום ההוא קידש המלך תוך החצר כי מזבח
הנחושת קטן מהיכל. bayom hahu kidesh hamelech toch hachatzar ki mizbe’ach hanechoshet
katan mehichal.
So the first opinion ר׳ יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads it as he
sanctified literally the courtyard, כי מזבח הנחושת ki mizbe’ach hanechoshet he reinterprets,
because even the new the replacement altar, the new altar was too
small. Okay that's the way ר׳ יהודה Rabbi Yehuda reads it. He
sanctified the courtyard because even the new altar was too small. Even
though it says the copper altar it means the replacement for the
copper altar. ר׳ יוסי Rabbi Yossi says no, this תוך החצר toch
hachatzar means that he sanctified the new altar that was in the
חצר. chatzar. Okay he sanctified the new so for him it means
he sanctified the new altar because the literally the old altar was
for him it means the old one was too
small and therefore he sanctified the new one. But for some reason,
I don't know why he feels that according to that read he
has to read קטן katan as less literal. It doesn't just mean,
it doesn't mean it was too small, it means it wasn't up
for the task. He invalidated it because it wasn't up for the
task. Again, it's not clear to me why we have to now
read קטן katan to be metaphorical. I don't know, maybe they explain
it there. It is too small. Anyway, he says, okay. הקטן אומר
לחבירו פלוני ננס ופסול לעבודה. Hakatan omer lachaveiro ploni nannas upasul la'avoda.
You may that again,
it's a little bit whatever, it's not compliment- it's not, it's not
proper sensitivity language that we would sort of have nowadays. But anyway,
קטן katan doesn't work with the expectancy פסול. מזבח הנחשת פסול
מהכ- פסל. Mizbeach hanechoshet pasul mehach- pasal. Yeah, right, somehow it was,
it wasn't, it fell short of the task. But I don't know
why it doesn't just say literally it was too small, like what's
bothering him? According to the way he reads it, right? It was,
anyway, fine. Moving on. So the גמרא says, anyway, okay.
So the גמרא says like this, רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, one minute.
Oh
wait wait, no no no, I understand. Oh no no, I'm sorry.
I'm mixing up the two opinions. I apologize. I apologize. Let's do
it one more time. I can tell you the opinions, I understand
now. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda says it means that literally the new
one, the old one, he says that they sanctified the courtyard, let's
get it right, because the new one wasn't big enough. Comes רבי
יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi says to רבי יהודה,
Rebbi Yehuda, comes רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi and רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi
says the new מזבח mizbeach was big enough. Yeah,
I'm still not getting it. The new מזבח Mizbe'ach was big enough,
so just say that means that the copper one, I don't know.
All right, anyway, moving on.
Anyway, so now the גמרא says like this, ורבי יהודה שפיר קאמר
רבי יוסי. VeRebbi Yehuda shapir ka'amar Rebbi Yosi. So now we've got
a problem. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi proved that it was a hundred
times as big. So what do you mean that the new altar
wasn't big enough? It was big enough, it was a hundred times
as big. So רבי יהודה לטעמיה דאמר מזבח שעשה משה גדול היה.
Rebbi Yehuda leta'amei de'amar mizbeach she'asa Moshe gadol haya. No,
רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda holds not these dimensions. It wasn't five by
five with a middle of one by one. That's incorrect, okay? It
was actually much bigger than that, okay? דתניא, Detanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, we've got another debate of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
and רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, how to read it and how literal
to read something. דתניא, Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, חמש אמות
אורך וחמש אמות רוחב דברי רבי יוסי. Chamesh amot orech vechamesh amot
rochav divrei Rebbi Yosi. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi says literally it was
five by five, the altar of משה, Moshe, so the usable space
was one by one. And that's why he said the new altar
of שלמה Shlomo was a hundred times as big, or excuse me,
four hundred times as big. And since the new one of שלמה
Shlomo was four hundred times as big, it obviously could handle all
the sacrifices. Okay, that's רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yosi. רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda
can't go that way. Why? רבי יהודה אומר נאמר כאן רבוע ונאמר
להלן רבוע. Rebbi Yehuda omer ne'emar kan ravu'a vene'emar lehalan ravu'a. Here
it says רבוע, ravu'a, and by יחזקאל Yechezkel it says רבוע. ravu'a.
מה להלן מאמצעיתו, Ma lehalan me'emtzi'ato, by יחזקאל Yechezkel when it does
the measurement and it uses the word square, it's measuring from the
center of the square. Okay, twelve אמה ama on each side, I
believe, היה מודד. haya moded. אף כאן מאמצעיתו היה מודד. Af kan
me'emtzi'ato haya moded. So here too when it says five by five
רבוע, ravu'a, it means five by five measured from the center of
the square. So if that's true, if it's five by five measured
by the center of the square, it's ten by ten and it's
a hundred. Even if you chop in one on each, one for
the corners and one for the walk around, okay, it's still six
by six which is thirty-six. And thirty-six compared to four hundred which
we had by the other thing is basically an eleven to one
ratio. So according to him, the one of משה Moshe was only,
the one of שלמה Shlomo was eleven times bigger and it wasn't
big enough to handle, if they did one thousand on משה's Moshe
and they needed to do twenty-two thousand there, that's why he says
the one of שלמה Shlomo was not big enough to handle it.
It was only eleven times bigger than the one of משה. Moshe.
Okay, והתם מנלן, Vehatam minalan, now there where do you know by
יחזקאל Yechezkel that it means measured from the center? דכתיב והאריאל, Dechtiv
veha'ariel, האריאל ariel
which is the word for the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, שתים עשרה אמה לכל
רוח. Shteim esrei ama lechol ruach.
It's twelve אמה ama to each direction and it uses the word-
oh אין אלא שתים עשרה על שתים עשרה. Ein ela shteim esrei
al shteim esrei.
Maybe it means twelve by twelve, not twelve measured from the center?
כשהוא אומר על ארבעת רבעיו, Keshehu omer al arba'at reva'av, by all
four of its sides, מלמד שמאמצעו היה מודד. melamed sheme'emtzo haya moded.
So somehow that's teaching you you start in the middle and you
go twelve אמה ama in each four directions. Okay, fine. So now
we've got this idea that according to רבי יהודה, Rebbi Yehuda, the
new altar of שלמה Shlomo was only eleven times more usable space
than the one of משה, Moshe, and therefore they couldn't use it
for all of these altars, they had to sanctify the actual ground
itself. Whereas according to רבי יוסי, Rebbi Yosi, it was a hundred-
it was four hundred times more usable space and they did not
need to sanctify the ground itself. Now, ורבי יוסי, VeRebbi Yosi, now
we're almost now we're going to have another fascinating debate that doesn't
link to this, but another fascinating any question of how literal you
are between רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Eventually
to remind you where we're going to have to circle back. We're
going to have to circle back is that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
is saying that they could use the ground of the עזרה Azara
since the altar of שלמה Shlomo was not big enough they needed
22,000 and it was only 11 times bigger than משה Moshe and
they couldn't use the altar of שלמה Shlomo they had to sanctify
the עזרה Azara itself. So what does he say? Does he really
think you can sprinkle the blood on the floor of the עזרה,
Azara, right? So we're going to see a difference between the blood
stuff you do for קרבנות Korbanot and the other stuff like the
burning of the אימורים eimurim and so on. That's where this is
going, that even though he's got them sanctifying the floor because the
altar wasn't big enough, that's not going to be true about all
things. Blood requires the מזבח Mizbe'ach getting back to our focus on
blood. We're not going to finish that thought today but that's where
it's going. Let's deal though with another debate of רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosi and רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So now the גמרא says like
this: ורבי יוסי, VeRabbi Yosi, now רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi would say
back you רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda think רבוע ravua you learn it
from יחזקאל Yechezkel to mean that five אמות amos measured from the
center in each direction. No, כי גמר גזירה שוה, ki gamar gezeirah
shavah, you know what he does with the רבוע? ravua? בגובה הוא
דגמר begovah hu degamar
to tell you something about the height of the מזבח Mizbe'ach, of
משה. Moshe. דתניא detanya we taught: ושלש אמות קומתו v'shalosh amos komaso
three אמות amos high, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. So now
here's fascinating how radically different their proportions are. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says the Torah says 3 by 5 by 5, okay, and then
it uses the word רבוע. ravua. So comes רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
and he says, so רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says the 5 by
5 really means 10 by 10, okay, it's much bigger, I don't
know why I started doing that, but the 3 is literal, okay,
so the 3 is literal, 3, and then 10 by 10. Okay
you've got a very big,
a low and a wide altar, okay. 3 would be what like
about 5 feet? and 10 would be like what like 15 feet?
Okay that would be the altar for in the time of משה,
Moshe, right? That would be for רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. Okay the
3 is literal, the 5 we expand out to be 10, okay.
Comes along רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and he says no, the 5
is literal, so it remains 5 by 5, but the 3 is
not literal. And what we're really going to do is the altar's
going to be 10 high. Okay it's going to be 10 by
5 by 5. So for רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi this is the
way the altar looked and for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that's the
way the altar looked, like radically
different. Okay. So where's he going to get 10 height if it
says 3? From that word רבוע. ravua. Okay so the גמרא says
like this: בגובה הוא דגמר דתניא ושלש אמות קומתו begovah hu degamar
detanya v'shalosh amos komaso 3 אמות amos high, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei
Rabbi Yehuda.
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's like it is: 3 high but
10 by 10 wide. רבי יוסי אומר נאמר כאן רבוע ונאמר להלן
רבוע. Rabbi Yosi omer neemar kan ravua v'neemar lehalan ravua. It says
here רבוע ravua and it says over there, okay the what's the
over there? By the מזבח הזהב, mizbeach hazahav, by the gold altar,
רבוע. ravua. And there it's 1 by 1 by 2, okay that
golden altar. The height is twice of the width and the length.
מה להלן גובה פי שנים כארכו אף כאן פי שנים כארכו. mah
lehalan govah pi shenayim k'arko af kan pi shenayim k'arko. The same
way there the height is double the other two, you know, the
width and the length,
here too it's double. So if this is 5 by 5 the
height is 10. That's what the word רבוע ravua is going to
tell you. So we're going to have to figure out what 3
means if it really means 10 high. Okay but that's רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yosi position. אמר לו רבי
יהודה, Amar lo Rabbi Yehuda, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said to him:
והלא כבר נאמר ואת חצר מאה באמה וקומת חמש וכולי vahalo kevar
neemar v'es chatzer meah ba'amah v'komos chamesh v'chulei etc. אפשר כהן עומד
על גבי מזבח ועבודה בידו וכל העם רואים אותו מבחוץ? efshar kohen
omed al gabei mizbeach va'avodah beyado v'chol ha'am roim oso mibachutz? He
says I don't get you! The כהן kohen is going to stand
up here 10 אמות amos off the ground, okay, 15 feet off
the ground, his feet are 15 feet off the ground. Now do
you know how high the קלעים klaim were around the חצר? chatzer?
5 feet? Okay so here he is going to be not 5
feet, 5 אמות. amos. He's going to be way visible. That's the
whole purpose for, you know, for the curtains is that this is
a holy thing, it's an intimate scene, it's not, you know, public
and whatever that everybody gets to see which sort of like, you
know, devalues it, right? So if, you know, here he is, he's
saying that everybody can watch him, like what's the meaning of those
קלעים klaim and where's the proper intimacy that there's supposed to go
on here, right? So it doesn't make any sense. According to him,
this is only
3 feet... 3 אמות. amos. The כהן kohen can stand here and
there's still two more אמות amos height of it of curtains, okay?
Which although a person's height is more than 2 אמות, amos, but
okay, maybe you see the top of his head but it's not
like all totally exposed. Here it's totally exposed. All right? So he
says: וכל העם רואים אותו מבחוץ. v'chol ha'am roim oso mibachutz. אמר
לו רבי יוסי, Amar lo Rabbi Yosi, so
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says: you know what? The same way I
made this 10 high even though it was only supposed to be
3 high, I'm going to make the curtains 15 high even though
the פסוקים pesukim say they're only 5. והלא כבר נאמר ואת קלעי
החצר ואת מסך שער החצר אשר על המשכן ועל המזבח סביב. vahalo
kevar neemar v'es kal'ei hachatzer v'es masach shaar hachatzer asher al hamishkan
v'al hamizbeach saviv. So it says the קלעים klaim that are on
the משכן mishkan and around the מזבח Mizbe'ach סביב. saviv.
So it says now, ולא כבר נאמר ואת קלעי החצר ואת מסך
שער החצר אשר על המשכן ועל המזבח סביב. Velo k'var ne'emar ve'et
kal'ei hechatzer ve'et masach sha'ar hechatzer asher al hamishkan ve'al hamizbe'ach saviv.
מה משכן עשרה אמות אף מזבח עשרה אמות. Ma Mishkan asara amot
af Mizbe'ach asara amot. The same way when they surround the משכן
Mishkan and the משכן Mishkan is ten אמות amot high, it's another
evidence for him that this is five אמות amot high. It says
these קלעים kla'im surround the מזבח Mizbe'ach and the משכן. Mishkan. So
the same way we know that the משכן Mishkan is ten אמות
amot high, that's explicit, okay, and so it also surrounds this that's
ten אמות amot high. But now we've still got our problem. ואומר
קלעים חמש עשרה
אמה על הכתף. Ve'omer kla'im chamesh esreh ama al hakatef. So now
here he's going to do a not at all פשט pshat reading
of it because it says the קלעים kla'im here it says are
fifteen אמה. ama. Now when it says fifteen אמה ama it means
the width. They're like fifteen אמה ama by fifteen אמה ama right
and then there's an opening door here, it means that they go
like the width is fifteen אמה. ama. But he's going to choose
to read it that it means that their height is fifteen אמות.
amot. ומה תלמוד לומר חמש אמות? Uma talmud lomar chamesh amot? So
what so okay I'm now going to say that these קלעים kla'im
are actually fifteen אמות. amot. Boom. Okay, they're fifteen. So what does
the פסוק pasuk mean when it says five אמות? amot? So it
says ומה תלמוד לומר חמש אמות? uma talmud lomar chamesh amot? משפת
המזבח ולמעלה. misfat hamizbe'ach u'lema'ala. It means five אמות amot higher than
the thing it's surrounding. It's surrounding the משכן, Mishkan, it's surrounding the
מזבח, Mizbe'ach. these are five אמות. amot. So we took a פסוק
pasuk that said five and we turned it into fifteen. We took
a פסוק pasuk that said three and we turned it into ten.
Now five and fifteen we can live with maybe, that the five
is measuring five higher than the tops, you know, than the thing
it's surrounding. So maybe that's a way of reading it. But how
does three mean ten? And what we're going to say the way
three means ten is it means three from the top. Okay, it's
going to be three, six, and then there's going to be like
one here, the horns. Okay and that's how three is going to
mean ten. So he does a radical re-read. Okay, רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda also does a re-read to make it very wide, but here
he gets three to mean ten and he gets five to mean
fifteen. ומה תלמוד לומר חמש אמות? Uma talmud lomar chamesh amot? משפת
המזבח ולמעלה. misfat hamizbe'ach u'lema'ala. מה תלמוד לומר שלוש אמות קומתו? Ma
talmud lomar shalosh amot kumato? שלוש אמות shalosh amot משפת סובב ולמעלה
misfat sovev u'lema'ala from the walk around and higher. Okay, so if
there was a line here for walk around or some type of
a protrusion, it's three אמות amot higher. Okay, okay now רבי יהודה
כי גמר גזירה שוה ברוחבה הוא דגמר. Rabbi Yehuda ki gamar gezeira
shava berochba hu degamar. But רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says no,
the רבוע ravu'a tells you it means five from each direction, which
is a reasonable read of the פסוק, pasuk, okay, and he does
not say it means that you make this go high. All right,
so here's the debate. For רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it was long
and wide, for him it was high and the three means ten
and whatever. Now bottom line is all of this factors into the
fact that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said the מזבח of שלמה Shlomo
was not big enough to handle the new business, it was only
eleven times bigger and they had to sanctify the floor, and רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose said it was a hundred times bigger and they
didn't have to sanctify the floor. So eventually we're going to have
to get back to the idea that for רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
they sanctified the floor to operate as a מזבח, but does it
literally mean it could do everything for the מזבח or is there
a difference between the blood and the other stuff? So that's why
we're bringing this all in to be קשור kashur to this issue
of a chipped מזבח that you can't use that for the blood
and for שחיטה, shechita, but it's okay when it comes to other
things like burning of the קטורת ketoret to not have a מזבח.
Okay, so we will continue with this tomorrow.